Pinelands Folklife Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Field documentation arranged by fieldworker, Field photography descriptions are copied directly from B and C logs via Optical Character Recognition, so errors and abbreviations exist.
  - Elaine Thatcher
    - Field recordings on reel-to-reel audio tape
      - Sitting around at the home of the Putiris, Hammonton, New Jersey, November 17, 1983, AFC 1991/023: AFS 24040; Elaine Thatcher; PFP-83-RET-029; RXA 6096; 1 audiotape reel (7 inch); Carl Fleischhauer
      - Interview with Salvatore Putiri, Sr., Salvatore Putiri, Jr., Ralph Putiri and Charlie Palmieri: making grave blankets, Hammonton, New Jersey, November 17, 1983, AFC 1991/023: AFS 24041; Elaine Thatcher; PFP-83-RET-030; RXA 6097; 1 audiotape reel (7 inch); Carl Fleischhauer, Sue Samuelson
      - Making grave blankets, Hammonton, New Jersey, November 17, 1983, AFC 1991/023: AFS 24042; Elaine Thatcher; PFP-83-RET-031; RXA 6098; 1 audiotape reel (7 inch); Carl Fleischhauer, Sue Samuelson
    - Miscellaneous documentation
      - Miscellaneous documentation; ephemera, Elaine Thatcher; 16 manuscript pages (8.5 x 14 inch or smaller) (Box-folder 17/167)
    - Final report
      - Final report, Elaine Thatcher; 17 manuscript pages (8.5 x 14 inch or smaller) (Box-folder 17/168)
  - Other fieldworkers: Brian Griggsby, Bill Teitler, Jay Orr, Paula J. Johnson, Frank Astemborski
    - Field photography on color slide film
      - C log (color photo log), American Folklife Center; 14 manuscript pages (8.5 x 14 inch or smaller) (Box-folder 17/169)
      - Baking bread, Nesco, New Jersey, November 10, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CBG-001; Brian Griggsby; PFP-83-CBG-001; 15 color film transparencies (35mm slide)
        1, Leo Landy in kitchen with granddaughter. Loaves of kneaded bread on table, ready to put in pans. G-Nesco; 26GT; 2, Leo putting bread in pan. Hazel to his right; 3, Same; 4-5, Leo punching dough; 6, Leo putting bread in oven; 7-9, Putting last loaves in pan; 10-11, Between bread-baking and lunch; 12-15, After lunch, drinking coffee and conversing.
      - Visit to Nature's Florist Supplies, home of Hazel and Leo Landy, Nesco, New Jersey, February 21, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CBT-001; Bill Teitler; PFP-83-CBT-001; 19 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Mary Hufford
        G-Nesco; 26GT; 1, Leo Landy in shop behind his house, holding armful of immortel (Gnaphallum Obtusifolia) aka "old field balsam", Hazel thinks because it grew abundantly near an area called "Old field" (see PFP-83-FMH1117). Aka "sweet everlasting", "rabbit tobacco" (in the mountain south; Hazel received a request for rabbit tobacco, which she was unable to fill, since she knows it as "immortel.") Note the plant specimens, dried, named and displayed over the window behind Hazel's head. They help gatherers to identify what it is they should gather). Decorative plants processed & sold by Landies; 2, Cat's paw(Eriophorum?), a swamp loving plant, gathered in early autumn; 3, Immortel (Gnaphalium Obtusifolia); 4, Italian broccoli (Cruciferae) (?); 5, Narrow leaved cattail (Typha Angustifoia)?; 6, Milkweed pods (Asclepias sp.); 7, Bayberry spray, aka common wax myrtle (Myrica sp.); 8; 9; 10, Teasel (Dipsacus s p.); 11, Landy in shop; 12, Landy in shop; 13, Baby oats; 14, Coffee grass (a sedge); 15, Golden millet (Setaria lutescens Hub) Graminae; 16, 17, Italian wheat? Wild Wheat?; 18, Leo Landy, in doorway of shop; 19, Leo Landy, in doorway of shop; 20, Hazel Landy (plant) gathering
      - Visit to Nature's Florist Supplies, at the home of Hazel and Leo Landy, Nesco, New Jersey, February 21, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CBT-002; Bill Teitler; PFP-83-CBT-002; 13 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Mary Hufford
        G-Nesco; 26GT 1, Sand grass (declared off-limits to pickers, by the state); 2, Okra pods; 3, Wild mustard grass (?); 4, Lotus pod (they tried unsuccessfully to introduce these into some local streams); 5, okra pods; 6, deer skull, with antlers, hanging in shed; 7, Landy, inside his pine-cone popping shed; 8, Landy, inside his pine-cone popping shed; 9, Landy, outside his pine-cone popping shed; 10, Landy, inside curing shed. Yellow yarrow at lower left, wild mustard and pepper grass hanging from roof; 11, Peppergrass (Lepidium Virginicum) (?); 12, Sacks of pine cones, Hazel Landy, Mary Hufford (w/tape recorder) and Leo Landy in curing shed; 13, Landy walking into workshop from rear (plant)
      - Four-wheeling at Hidden Lakes, New Jersey, September 18, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CJO-001; Jay Orr; PFP-83-CJO-001; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Mary Hufford
        1-20, scenes of three-wheeling and four-wheeling at G-Hidden Lakes; 53GT. (See PFP-83-RMH-006-007 for details); 19, Mary Hufford interviewing Dave Densbower and Chris Loveland from the Bucks County (Pa) All-Terrain Vehicle club. (NB also numbers 5 and 15.); 32, Mary Hufford interviewing Nevin Ianuzzi, whose fourwheel vehicle just made it successfully through the mud hole.
      - Four-wheeling at Hidden Lakes, New Jersey, September 18, 1983, AFC 1991/023: CJO-002; Jay Orr; PFP-83-CJO-002; 12 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Mary Hufford
        1,2,5, Mary Hufford interviewing members of the Bucks County, Pa. All-Terrain Vehicle Club: Dave Densbower, Chris Loveland. They come here for three-wheeling around the dirt roads and sand hills. G-Hidden Lakes; 53GT; 6,9,12, Mary Hufford interviewing Nevin Ianuzzi, of Medford, and his wife, who come here for four-wheeling. (See PFP-83-RMH-006-007 for details); 3,4,7,8,10,11, Various scenes of the place, a lake gouged out by a sand and gravel mining company. Land use regulations stipulate that the companies must create lakes whenever they hit water, and the various lakes they've produced throughout the area have become recreational space for three-and-four wheelers.
      - Railbirding on Patuxent River near Upper Marlboro, Maryland, September 7, 1984, AFC 1991/023: CPJ84-001; Paula J. Johnson; PFP-84-CPJ-001; 17 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Gerald E. Parsons, Carl Fleischhauer
        1, Frank Astemborski's New Jersey railbird skiff, towed by Gerald Parson's sneakbox; 2, Jim Owings and Carl Fleischhauer towing Owings' Maryland railbird skiff past the pilings of the abandoned Chesapeake Beach Railroad Bridge. Note Mount Calvert in background.; 3, Carl Fleischhauer, photographer, jim Owings, Railbirder tending the skiff; 4, View of Maryland style skiff with pushpole. Note rocker in boat hull; 5-17, Scenes of railbirding. # 8 spatterdocks in foreground. #14 Jim Owings in bow, Frank Astemborski pushing.
      - Railbirding on the Patuxent River, Upper Marlboro, Maryland, September 7, 1984, AFC 1991/023: CPJ84-002; Paula J. Johnson; PFP-84-CPJ-002; 5 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Gerald E. Parsons, Carl Fleischhauer
        1-5, Jim Owings cleaning trash out of skiff after the hunt.
      - Railbirding on the Maurice River, New Jersey, September 24, 1984, AFC 1991/023: CFA-001; Frank Astemborski; PFP-84-CFA-001; 20 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Gerald E. Parsons
        1, Pushers and gunners waiting for the tide; 2, Jim Owings; 3-5, Pushers launching their boats; 6, Ken Camp pushing Gerald Parsons. Note apparent speed of skiff; 7-9, Going down river to the meadow; 10, Shows Ken Camp thrashing reeds to flush birds; 14, Walter Camp pushing Walter Monier; 20, Gunners and pushers relaxing after the hunt.
      - Railbirding on the Maurice River, New Jersey, October 24, 1984, AFC 1991/023: CFA-002; Frank Astemborski; PFP-84-CFA-002; 10 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Gerald E. Parsons
        Pushers and gunners relaxing after hunt.
      - Aerial photographs, Mullica River area, New Jersey, between 1983 and 1985, AFC 1991/023: CLP85-001; PFP-85-CLP-001; 18 color film transparencies (35mm slide); Not in log
    - Field photography on black-and-white film
      - B log (black-and-white photo log), American Folklife Center; 14 manuscript pages (8.5 x 14 inch or smaller); Black-and-white log starts on page 12 (Box-folder 17/169A)
      - Railbirding on the Patuxent River, Ann Arundel County, Maryland, September 7, 1984, AFC 1991/023: 235044-01; Paula J. Johnson; PFP-84-BPJ-235044-01; 21 black-and-white film negatives (35mm)
        1, High tide on Ann Arundel Co. side of Patuxent River; Tree line (rear) is on embankment of old abandoned Chesapeake Beach Railroad; 2-7, Astemborski pushing Owings; 8, Astemborski; 10, Pushpole foot; 11-12, Astemborski pushing Owings. Jug Bay looking east toward Spignel farm; 13-14, Astemborski; 15-21, Owings cleans trash out of skiff before storing boat. Note use of handmade wooden balling scoop to wash out mud and reed. Looking west across Jug Bay to Jackson Landing. Stand in aluminum jon-boat made by Frank Astemborski to hold gun if marcher buoys when pushing solo. Camoflage paint on Owings' jon-boat indicates it is also used for ducking.
  - Post-fieldwork documentation
    - Hard copies containing sensitive materials deleted from disks (Box-folder 17/170)
    - Informants' business cards (Box-folder 17/171)
    - Reference slides and contact sheets, Dennis McDonald and Robert Noonan (Box-folder 17/172)
- Series 4: Final products
  Summary: Materials generated during the product development phase of the project, including final reports, project publications, presentation materials, post-project correspondence, and promotional materials, correspondence, and publications associated with the exhibition and conference New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment.
  - Administrative Coordinator's report and summary of archiving phase, American Folklife Center; 80 manuscript pages (8.5 x 14 inch or smaller) (Box-folder 17/173)
  - Post-Survey Fieldworkers Meeting, January 24, 1984 to January 26, 1984 (Box-folder 17/173)
  - American Folklore Society papers given by Sue Samuelson, Jens Lund, and Elaine Thatcher (Box-folder 18/174)
  - Computer materials; description of database, sample printouts, guidelines for editing, keywords (Box-folder 18/175)
  - Briefing for New Jersey Congressional Staff; slide presentation materials, invitation letter, delegation list, fact sheet, and presentation (Box-folder 18/176)
  - Cranberries; recipe booklet, preliminary drafts, and recipes (Box-folder 18/177)
  - Miscellaneous post-project correspondence, 1983 to 1991 (Box-folder 18/178)
  - Pinelands Folklife Project slide presentations, brochures, workshops (Box-folder 18/179)
  - Folk Studies: Exploring the Potential for New Jersey Museum Collections Museums Council of New Jersey conference poster, April 7, 1984 (Box-folder 21/201 (Oversize))
  - Library of Congress American Folklife Center Launches Field Survey of Pinelands National Reserve in New Jersey. Press release from Library of Congress Information Office, September 9, 1983 (Box-folder 19/180)
  - American Folklife Center Launches Field Survey of Pinelands National Reserve in New Jersey in Library of Congress Information Bulletin: 42 no. 37 (1983): 309-310, 1983 (Box-folder 19/180)
  - Folklife Center Holds Briefing on New Jersey Pinelands Project (Box-folder 19/180)
  - Issues of Folklife Center News, 1984 to 1985 (Box-folder 19/180)
  - Folklife Annual 1985: A publication of the American Folklife Center at the Library of Congress, 1985 (Box-folder 19/181)
  - Draft of Final Report (Box-folder 19/182)
  - Hufford, Mary. One Space, Many Places: Folklife and Land Use in New Jersey's Pinelands National Reserve: Report and Recommendations to the New Jersey Pinelands Commission for Cultural Conservation in the Pinelands National Reserve. Washington, D.C.: American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, 1986 (Box-folder 19/183)
    Pinelands Folklife Project final report. Includes hard copy and microfiche copy.
  - Proposal for exhibit, New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment; planning grant (Box-folder 19/184)
  - Promotional materials and ephemera produced in conjunction with New Jersey State Museum exhibit New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment, 1987 (Box-folder 19/185)
  - Exhibit announcement/poster for New Jersey State Museum exhibit New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment, 1987, 6 copies (Box-folder 21/203 (Oversize))
  - Exhibit correspondence with New Jersey State Council on the Arts, New Jersey Historical Commission, New Jersey State Museum (Box-folder 19/186)
  - Proposal and promotional materials for exhibit catalog, Pinelands Folklife (Box-folder 19/187)
  - Exhibit catalog Pinelands Folklife (Box-folder 19/187)
  - Planning and promotional materials for video Pinelands Sketches (Box-folder 20/188)
    Includes schedule of questions for interview subjects
  - Pinelands Sketches, March 4, 1987, AFC 1991/023: MV02; VBV 5734; 1 Umatic videocassette (30 minute): sd., color
    Pinelands Sketches, produced in 1987 by the New Jersey Network with support from the New Jersey Historical Commission and the New Jersey State Council on the Arts, documents railbird hunting, cranberry harvesting, cedar farming, garvey building, and fox hunting in the Pinelands area of New Jersey.
  - Unedited footage of a fox hunt in the Pinelands area of New Jersey, circa 1987, Tails fox hunt cloudy day; 2 tape reels (30 minute): si., color (Boxes 26-27)
    Unedited footage of a fox hunt in the Pinelands area of New Jersey. This footage was likely produced in 1987 for Pinelands Sketches but was not used in the final product.
  - Proposal and promotional materials for Pinefest exhibit opening and educational workshop series at the State Museum (Box-folder 20/189)
  - Proposal and promotional materials for conference New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment (Box-folder 20/190)
  - New Jersey Pinelands: Tradition and Environment, a Conference at New Jersey State Museum Auditorium, March 14, 1987, 4 copies (Box-folder 21/202 (Oversize))
    Conference poster
  - Newspaper publicity for exhibit, catalog, workshops, video, and conference (Box-folder 20/191)
  - Post-project articles about Pinelands issues appearing in local, regional, and national newspapers and periodicals (Box-folder 20/192)
  - Articles and reviews about the Pinelands Folklife Project and its products (Box-folder 20/193)
  - Copy of drawing of home of Joanne Vanistendal, Van Dal Lake, Medford, New Jersey (Box-folder 21/198 (Oversize))
- Series 5: Maps of New Jersey Pinelands, Unprocessed.
  Summary: Includes collected map publications such as aerial, geological, land-use, oceanographic, and topological maps of the Pinelands National Reserve produced by federal, state, and local government agencies. Also includes maps created or collected in the course of fieldwork, such as hand-drawn maps of yards and residences.
Bibliography
Related publications
Hufford, Mary. Chaseworld: Foxhunting and Storytelling in New Jersey's Pine Barrens. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, c1992.
Loomis, Ormond H, ed. Cultural Conservation: The Protection of Cultural Heritage in the United States, Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1983
Moonsammy, Rita Zorn, and David Steven Cohen. Pinelands Folklife. New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press, c1987.
New Jersey Pinelands Commission. New Jersey Pinelands Comprehensive Management Plan: A Progress Report on the First Three Years of Implementation. New Lisbon, N.J.: New Jersey Pinelands Commission, 1983.
NJN Videos. Railbirding. Trenton, N.J.: NJN Videos, 1986.
NJN Videos. The Sea Bright Skiff. Trenton, N.J.: NJN Videos, 1991.